In the last lesson,
we covered the basics
of semantic search and
saw that it worked
pretty well for a
good amount of use cases.
But we also saw some
edge cases and saw how
things could go a little bit wrong.
In this lesson, we're going to deep
dive on retrieval and cover a
few more advanced methods for overcoming
those edge cases.
I'm really excited by this
because I think retrieval
is something that is
new and a lot of the techniques we're
talking about have popped up
in the past few months or so. And
this is a cutting edge
topic and so you
guys are going to be right at the
forefront. Let's have some
fun.
In this lesson, we're
going to talk about retrieval. This
is important at query time, when
you've got a query that comes in
and you want to retrieved
the most relevant splits. We
talked in the previous
lesson about semantic
similarity search, but we're
going to talk about a few
different and more advanced
methods here. The first one
we're going to cover is Maximum Marginal Relevance,
or MMR. And so
the idea behind this is that
if you just always
take the documents that
are most similar to
the query in the
embedding space, you may actually miss
out on diverse information,
as we saw in
one of the edge cases. In this example, we've
got a chef asking about all white mushrooms.
And so if we take
a look at the most similar
results, those would be the first
two documents, where they have a lot
of information similar to the query
about a fruiting
body and being all white. But
we really want to
make sure that we
also get other information, like the fact that
it's really poisonous. And so this
is where using
MMR comes into play, as
it will select for a
diverse set of documents.
The idea behind MMR is
that we send a query in,
and then we initially get
back a set of responses, with
"fetch_k" being a parameter that we
can control in order
to determine how many
responses we get. This is based solely
on semantic similarity. From
there, we then work with that
smaller set of documents
and optimize for not
only the most relevant ones, based
on semantic similarity, but
also ones that are diverse. And
from that set of documents, we
choose a final "k" to
return to the user.
Another type of retrieval we can
do is what we call self-query. So
this is useful when you
get questions that aren't solely
about the content that
you want to look
up semantically, but also
include some mention of some
metadata that you want to
do a filter on. So let's take the
question, what are some
movies about aliens made
in 1980? This really has
two components to it. It's got a
semantic part, the aliens bit. So
we want to
look up aliens in our database
of movies. But it's also got
a piece that really refers to
the metadata about each
movie, which is the fact that
the year should be 1980.
What we can do is
we can use a language model itself to
split that original question
into two separate things,
a filter and a search
term. Most vector stores support a
metadata filter. So
you can easily filter
records based on metadata,
like the year being 1980.
Finally, we'll
talk about compression. This
can be useful to
really pull out only
the most relevant bits
of the retrieved passages. For
example, when asking a question, you
get back the whole
document that was stored, even
if only the first one or two sentences
are the relevant parts. With
compression, you can then run
all those documents through a language
model and extract the most relevant
segments and then
pass only the most relevant segments
into a final
language model call. This
comes at the cost
of making more calls
to the language model, but it's also
really good for focusing the final
answer on only the most important
things. And so it's a bit
of a tradeoff. Let's see these different
techniques in action. We're going to
start by loading the environment variables
as we always do.
Let's then import Chroma and OpenAI
as we used them before. And
we can see by looking at
the collection count that it's got
the 209 documents that we
loaded in before. Let's now go
over the example of max
marginal relevance. And so we'll
load in the text from the example where we
have the information about mushrooms. For
this example, we'll
create a small database
that we can just
use as a toy example. We've got our
question, and now we can run a
similarity search.
We'll set "k=2" to only return the two most
relevant documents. And we
can see that there is
no mention of the fact
that it is poisonous.
Let's now run it with MMR. While it's passing
"k=2", we still want
to return two documents, but let's set
"fetch_k=3", where we fetch all three documents
originally.
We can now see that the
information that is
poisonous is returned
among the documents
that we retrieved.
Let's go back to one
of the examples from
the previous lesson when
we asked about MATLAB
and got back documents
that had repeated information.
To refresh your memory, we
can take a look at
the first two documents, just
looking at the first
few characters because they're pretty
long otherwise, and we
can see that they're the same.
When we run
MMR on these results, we can see
that the first one is the same as
before because that's the most similar.
But when we go on to the second one,
we can see that it's different. It's getting
some diversity in the responses.
Let's now move on to the self-query example.
This is the one where we
had the question, what did
they say about regression in
the third lecture?
And it returned results from
not just the third lecture,
but also the first and the second.
If we were fixing this by hand,
what we would do is we'd
specify a metadata filter.
So we'd pass in this information
that we want the
source to be equal to the third lecture
PDF.
And then if we
look at the documents
that would be retrieved, they'd
all be from exactly that lecture.
We can use a language
model to do this for us, so we don't
have to manually specify that.
To do this, we'll
import a language model, OpenAI. We'll
import
a retriever called the self-query retriever, and
then we'll import attribute info,
which is where we
can specify different fields
in the metadata and
what they correspond to.
We only have two fields in the metadata,
source and page.
We fill out a description of the name,
the description, and the type for
each of these attributes.
This information is actually
going to be passed
to the language model, so it's
important to make it
as descriptive as possible.
We'll then specify some
information about what's actually
in this document store.
We'll initialize the language model, and
then we'll initialize the self-query retriever using
the "from_llm" method and passing in
the language model, the underlying vector
database
that we're going to query, the
information about the description
and the metadata, and
then we'll also pass
in "verbose=True".
Setting "verbose=True" will
let us see what's going
on underneath the hood
when the LLM infers
the query that should
be passed along with
any metadata filters.
When we run the self-query
retriever with this question, we
can see, thanks to "verbose=True", that
we're printing out what's going on under
the hood.
We get a query of regression,
this is the semantic bit,
and then we get a filter where we
have a comparator of
equals between the source
attribute and a value
of docs and then this path,
which is the path to
the third machine learning lecture.
So this is basically
telling us to do a lookup in the
semantic space on regression
and then do a filter where we only
look at documents that
have a source value of this value.
And so if we
loop over the documents
and print out the metadata,
we should see that they're
all from this third lecture.
And indeed they are.
So this is an example where the self-query
retriever can be used to
filter exactly on metadata.
A final retrieval technique
that we can talk
about is contextual compression.
And so let's
load in some relevant modules here, the
contextual compression retriever
and then an LLM chain extractor.
And what this is going to do is
this is going to
extract only the relevant
bits from each document
and then pass those
as the final return response.
We'll define a nice little
function to pretty print
out docs because they're often
long and confusing and
this will make it
easier to see what's going on.
We can then create a compressor
with the LLM chain extractor and
then we can create the contextual
compression retriever passing
in the compressor and then the
base retriever of the vector store.
When we now pass in the question,
what did they say
about MATLAB and we
look at the compressed docs,
if we look at the documents we get
back, we can see two things.
One, they are a lot
shorter than the normal documents.
But two, we've still got some of
this repeated stuff going
on and this is
because under the hood we're using
the semantic search algorithm.
This is what we solved by using MMR
from earlier in this lesson.
This is a good example of where you
can combine various techniques
to get the best possible results.
In order to do that, when we're
creating the retriever from
the vector database, we
can set the search type to MMR.
We can then rerun this and see that
we get back a
filtered set of results
that do not contain
any duplicate information.
So far, all the additional
retrieval techniques that we've
mentioned build on top
of a vector database.
It's worth mentioning that there's other
types of retrieval that don't use a
vector database at all and instead
uses other more traditional NLP techniques.
Here, we're going to recreate
a retrieval pipeline
with two different
types of retrievers, an
SVM retriever and a TF-IDF retriever.
If you recognize these terms from
traditional NLP or
traditional machine learning, that's
great.
If you don't, it's also fine. This is
just an example of
some other techniques that
are out there.
There are plenty more
besides these and I
encourage you to go
check out some of them.
We can run through
the usual pipeline of
loading and splitting pretty
quickly.
And then both of these
retrievers expose a from text
method.
One takes in an embedding module,
that's the SVM retriever, and
the TF-IDF retriever
just takes in the
splits directly.
Now we can use the other retrievers.
Let's pass in what did
they say about MATLAB
to the SVM retriever
and we can look
at the top document
we get back and we can see that
it mentions a lot
of stuff about MATLAB, so it's picking
up some good results there.
We can also try this out on the TF-IDF
retriever and we can
see that the results
look a little bit worse.
Now's a good time to pause and try out
all these different retrieval
techniques.
I think you'll notice that some of
them are better than
others at various things.
And so I'd encourage you to try
it out on a wide variety of questions.
The self query retriever
in particular is my favorite.
So I would suggest
trying that out with
more and more complex
metadata filters.
Even maybe making up
some metadata where there's
really nested metadata structures
and you can try
to get the LLM to infer that.
I think that's a lot of fun. I
think that's some
of the more advanced stuff out
there and so I'm really excited
to have been able to share
it with you.
Now that we've
talked about retrieval, we're going
to talk about the next
step in the process, which is
using these retrieved
documents to answer
the user question.